hello it's February 8th 2023 we're in
cohort three
and we're having our second discussion
on chapter one
so just a few
side notes before we jump to the
questions
uh first I'll place this in the chat
but
we can
um hey Maria are you recording the the
meeting yes I'm recording it with OBS
like on my local computer okay I'm sorry
oh no thank you for checking the icon
okay thanks for checking yes it doesn't
mention it it's like a yes
so last week we talked about neats and
scruffies
and those terms are due to Raj or shank
and it was actually last week that Roger
shank had passed away which I have just
placed in the chat
so
auspicious though tragic
and people may
find a lot of in this article by Harold
jarch
a lot of interesting
um
thoughts on learning by doing
teaching others to do this is the next
step in the education Revolution
and also there's a student's Bill of
Rights
that I had never seen from shank before
so there's a lot of interesting
um
pieces here
so for those who are interested
take a look and maybe see how we can
bring some of that
back to the textbook group
and then also awesome thanks
yeah
and then um I don't see Yana Here but
yesterday Jana and I
went to the step-by-step active
inference paper which I'll also put in
the chat is one that we reference all
the time
because it has a step-by-step building
of like static perception Dynamic
perception these are passive
interference and then action comes into
play
and we
use the ontology
to describe what was happening and use
latex in coda to write the equation
and then uh
made some tables
that allowed us to flip between
different ways of talking about what was
given and what we're calculating
wrote the pseudo code
made tables for every variable and
interpreted every column
so this was just for the static example
but it was a lot of fun
and I'll also put that
thanks Jonathan that's that sounds cool
too yeah so this was a lot of fun that
we had
and just uh there's definitely some
walls that we run up against like doing
vector and matrix multiplication in Coda
but it's a fun direction for making
really interactive and multimedia
um
systems all right so
let's go to chapter one
does anyone want to give any thought or
comment at all on chapter one
any thought or or
question at all
and then we'll jump into the questions
that the cohort has had on chapter one
it feels like a long while now since
reading it could have been last week
could have been last year
yeah feel free to raise your hand or
write in the chat
any comment or question that's
presenting itself to you today
or we will look into
the questions that
the cohort wrote
okay
it looks like we may have done this last
time
what is the relationship between policy
and environment maybe anyone can just
give a
summary or thought on that and then
we'll move it up
okay
yeah very informative comment thread
Brock go for it and then anyone else
um policies are
um selections on affordances
in uh like late in the foreign
environment
speak thanks yeah
and then let's look at the comment
thread
generative process stomach is empty
stomach emits a rumble that's a great
example
because the generative process
helps
frame it in terms of what it is which is
the process that passes observations to
the blanket this doesn't have to be
outside quote of the organism
so the true
status of the stomach
is an external state
with respect to the blanket States being
interception and the internal States
being
cognitive modeling of interception
generative process is just whatever
passes observations
so it doesn't have to be the niche
but in the case of exteroception
Vision hearing Etc
pockets coming into a server
then it is outside of the agents
but it doesn't have to be spatially
outside of the agents Jonathan
yeah we said that the generative process
is the thing that passes observations
um presumably it doesn't have to pass an
observation there can be things
happening in the outside world that we
don't have access to but may still be
part of our generative that what yeah
what is actually the generative process
of the real world
great point the generative process does
pass observations to the blanket
but that is not all it has to do
so it could have
um the extra the generative process
could have 10 variables
like the thunderstorm could have
temperature light sounds
but then we only have a microphone so
we're only perceiving sound
so the generative process is passing us
sounds
and then that is being used by the
agents
but that's not to say that the
generative process is only sound
and that comes back to to a
um
slightly more General point which is
that the state space of the generative
process doesn't have to be the same as
the state space of the cognitive model
foreign
processes can be other generative models
in the social setting as Jonathan is
pointing to that's sometimes called
thinking through other Minds
and let's look at this
it's cool when we can see a previous
question
on the notion of surprise is the agent's
perception not only affected by the
influence
of its environments but also an agent's
peers
so the agent's peers are updating their
beliefs in a collaborative fashion
what would be the extent of the update
to an agent's GM of perceptions if an
agent Witnesses the annihilation of one
of its peers for example something like
this
okay it's a wildebeest
people can check out the video
okay
Michael please
I I just have a question with respect
previously you wrote down that policy a
policy is a sequence of affordances and
I was wondering is it a sequence or is
it the one affordance
is it is a policy one affordance or is a
policy a sequence so is it can it be
more than one influence I was
of the understanding that the policy is
one affordance but maybe I'm confused
yeah good good
question and policy and affordance are
used slightly differently
for example in the reinforcement
learning setting but we won't
necessarily go there so if wardens are
the actions that can be taken in a
single moment
alternative actions that can be taken
so this could be movement up down left
right this could be an eye cicade up
down left right
policy is going to be a sequence of
those for a given time Horizon
so if the time Horizon is one
or the temporal depth of the model is
one
this is the same as affordances
but if the the temporal depth
were two
then it would be all combinations
of two affordances
so up up up down down left right right
left
how does it then work with
epistemic and pragmatic affordances at
some points in the book it says that
these are two aspects of one affordance
mm-hmm
yes great we we are going to get there
and here's what it's going to look like
and just to peek forward in chapter two
so
um Pi our policy
Pi for policy
G is expected free energy
expected free energy is going to be
calculated for every single policy
so again if that is temporal depth of
one it's just equivalent to the options
that can be taken in that moment
if this is a temporal depth of five then
it's the free energy expected free
energy of
up up up up up up up up up up up up down
now those different policies
are going to be evaluated according to
this single imperative expected free
energy
that's going to rank different policies
based upon their posterior likelihood
in reward slash reinforcement learning
you would rank policies by their
expected reward
in fep we're going to rank policies by
their expected free energy which is
going to describe their posterior
likelihood
different policies might be seen as
likely
for different reasons
and this equation can be partitioned in
different ways to understand that so a
policy might be seen as really good
let's just say it's good but that means
the same thing as saying it's a likely
policy
if it secures a lot of Information Gain
on the other hand a policy could be seen
as good or likely if it secures a lot of
pragmatic value
those both get projected down into the
expected free energy now
conversationally
people will say something like oh well
opening the book that's like an
epistemic affordance
that's compatible with what we're
talking about here
but the partition here would be like the
affordance is to open the book or not
open the book
and then the action selection to open
the book
is selected because it has a high
Information Gain
so the idea and one that we'll continue
to revisit is that you can get Behavior
that's able to exhibit
pragmatic values seeking components and
when those are unclear on how to pursue
come into an information seeking mode
through a unified imperative G
so we still do have epistemic epistemic
affordances in the conversational sense
but to be strict about it there are just
affordances which are the capacities for
action
and then different policies are selected
or not and we can partition that
differently and that partitioning May
reveal that a policy was selected
because it reduced information
had high epistemic value
reduced informational uncertainty should
I say
um or it was aligning observations with
preferences which is pragmatic value
foreign
can we relate policy with Goal I'm going
to just copy in these answers
page 101
chapter five well we'll come there
okay
any other
comments or questions on this topic
okay
Ali
uh actually about about Maria's question
uh that if we can relate policy uh with
goals
um well
maybe I don't know I if I can reiterate
that example I pointed out in the last
session about picking up uh a couple a
cop so yeah actually uh the the goal is
somehow
inherently Consolidated into our actions
and our policies uh or at least at our
goal directive actions uh so I pointed
out to an example
um
from
ritzalatian senegalia's book mirrors in
the brain which says that picking up a
cup of coffee can be done in various
ways depending on whether we are
drinking from it uh in which in that
case we would grasp it by the handle or
if we're washing it in that case we'll
grasp it by the rim or moving it out of
the way uh in that case we would grasp
it by the body so yeah actually in this
scenario selecting the appropriate
policy would necessarily require
considering the goal of that policy or
action
yes thank you and
we can talk about goals
but the way that it plays out in the
generative model there isn't a variable
that's called the goal
so here
um Jonathan wrote the goal is really
about minimizing expected free energy so
yes some kind of meta imperative is
to fulfill the minimization of free
energy
but let's think about like the goal is
to move uh the goal is to move the
coffee cup to the drying rack
that is actually going to be embedded in
the preference
we expect and prefer to see the cup on
the drying rack
oh I observed it in the sink I'm
surprised
maybe even anxious
what are the affordances
well
without going too deep into a motor
model
we could like grab or not grab move arm
left move arm right
and then some policy like move arm left
grab move arm right release the grab
that's a four-step policy
that has pragmatic value
again looking forward but we're going to
come to this in the coming weeks
that policy
has value and it's like a goal-oriented
policy because we reduce the Divergence
between our preferences and observations
so goal oriented or pragmatic Behavior
is loaded heavily in this pragmatic
value section
which at its heart has to do with the
um relationship between
preferences
and observations
that's why we talk about like expect
slash prefer
like
we talk about it as a preference
but the way that it plays out is again
not by preferred states are the most
rewarding but preferred states are the
most expected
you'll be least surprised when your body
temperature is in its preferred value
when your body temperature is out of
your preferences you'll be surprised how
are we going to bound that surprise free
energy
just as it's done in Bayesian statistics
how are you going to bound surprise
there's two ways you could change the
world or you could change your mind
changing your mind
depending on the time scale is like
perception or learning
changing the world happens through
action
so let's just say we're again surprised
at seeing the coffee cup
in the sink
changing our mind might look like
updating our model of where we expect to
see coffee cups so that we're not
surprised
oh it's normal that it's in the sink
so now I'm not surprised anymore so we
effectively reduce Surprise by learning
or you could reduce your
expected free energy by taking sequences
of action
and whether a generative model
learns or how it learns or or whether it
acts and how it acts that has to do with
the details of how the model are set up
why exploration and exploitation are
automatically balanced through policy
selection and active inference what does
it mean to say both are balanced
any
thought
or related idea here
Jonathan and anyone else
yeah I mean I think it's to to really
understand it you have to understand the
equation that you were just showing us
um where the information game is about
exploration we can think about about
exploration and the pragmatic is about
exploitation
um and so to really understand how
that's automatically balanced you have
to understand exactly where that
equation comes from I think
awesome totally agree yes it's captured
in
expected free energy calculation
so this equation is not necessarily the
solution it's not a strategy to
balancing explore exploit like depending
on what variables are set
you could result in a agent that
always goes for the right slot machine
or always takes the hint so it's not
that just by Framing it this way
the problem has been solved but this as
it turns out creates an incredible
flexible framework for fitting
parameters and testing different models
that include the wide diversity of
cognitive phenomena like attention and
all of these other complex phenomena so
it's like linear regression y equals MX
plus b
that's not a solution to the regression
it's the space in which lines are going
to be compared to each other
so expected free energy isn't the
solution to Adaptive policy
but it's a space in which policies can
be compared with each other how are they
going to be compared with each other
with expected free energy
what are some decompositions of expected
free energy
it turns out to have some very useful
decompositions
that connect us with
on one hand in the top line
the semantics
of value
broadly in terms of informational or
epistemic value and pragmatic or utility
value
so that's one huge connection because we
can think about special cases like if
there's no information to be gained
expected free energy is going to get
only pragmatic value
if there's no pragmatic value
then it is equivalent to a pure
information novelty approach
and it can do mixes
but there's other decompositions that
connect to the middle lines here
have to do with
um decision and control theory and then
this bottom line
points the way towards connections with
physics
where we see energy and entropy for
example in the Gibbs free energy
so that's kind of a doorway into physics
and thermodynamics
and it's this
these are all just different
decompositions of the same functional
foreign
it's a an advocate's
claim
that active inference simply balances
explore exploit
but a slightly more measured angle would
be
it frames the problem so that generative
models can be constructed and
parameterized
that are able to adaptively navigate
explore and exploit
any
preference for a question to go to next
or anyone please feel free to just raise
any questions coming to mind Michael and
then anyone else
yeah I was wondering this distinction
between exploration exploitation does it
only apply to the expected values or
also to the variational free energy
good question
um
we will come to explore the similarities
and differences between
variational free energy figure 2.5 F and
expected free energy G
equation 2.6
in short
variational free energy f
is taking in as arguments Q are beliefs
the variational distributions that
represent our beliefs and data
so in variational free energy we're
actually not engaged in policy selection
in expected free energy we are engaged
in policy selection
so variational free energy is a common
measure used in
machine learning and statistics
because of its ability to effectively
fit models Based on data
and then to really take the full octave
turn
and talk about not just
optimal fitting of data but not
overfitting which is like what
variational free energy does
in the expected free energy case is when
we actually get into the consideration
of alternate affordances yeah Michael
then anyone else
yeah yeah so so you're you're saying
that exploration exploitation relates to
the policy so to the somehow to the
Future
right but I can also engage right now uh
right now into an exploration or an
exploitation isn't that the case
um so it I mean it does not only relate
to the future I guess does it
or
or what I'm I'm misunderstanding there
so I can explore
right now not only in in a plan for the
future
okay Jonathan
yeah I'd say that by some exploration
and exploitation are sort of active
things you know even if it's in the
moment now
um it's still uh you know it may be some
sequence it may be relatively short but
it's still something about what's
happening now and where I want to be
um so I I think that you know even if
you're thinking about your exploration
in this moment it is really about what's
happening in some some future time that
you're attempting to do
nice thank you and thanks great thank
you yeah and and also like exploration
exploitation are kind of informal
terms to describe different behavioral
outcomes
they're not necessarily like formal
um and then also uh a great comment
there in the chat
um
I'll just put it in here
this is a good reminder that like
affordances and policies it's like
always come back to map and territory
there's the affordances that the person
can engage in and that's like the
territory if you really want to think
about it and wonder about it like what
can a body do but as modeled there are
modeler degrees of freedom in which
affordances are going to be considered
for the agent to do
so
go to the vending machine like that
could be you could have the affordance
go to the vending machine or go or not
go it's just binary or you could have
raise your quadricep muscle
and flex your calf muscle
so that's going to be a model that can
do a lot of other things
but then you're going to have to have
all of this parameterization just to be
able to get out of the chair
so how you coarse grain
action
is one of the major
modeler degrees of freedom
and challenges in action modeling
we'll come back to this more times
any just offhand comment or question
that someone has
foreign
following the question mark is just a
tracking device
okay
it's a Twitter thread
we're reading books
why you want to go with a computational
approach why not just go full on Gibson
plus dynamical systems
well
this should be very
um
relevant I'll just bring in update here
actually Maxwell also had a response on
that tweet
okay let's let's start
what what
do you remember or what was the response
oh here responds to this oh yeah and
there's active inference wow
look at that foundational
Atlas Atlas Shrugged
do you remember what his response was
Ollie
uh yeah he somehow
um
well there's just the word uh was that
those two are not necessarily
exclusively mutual
and I mean I mean uh mutually exclusive
sorry but uh actually he's writing a
paper to show the relevance between the
two uh and uh yeah they're more
compatible than uh some people might
think so
uh
let me find the exact tweet thank you
yeah like
if it comes to conceptual
understanding
almost everything is compatible
it's like just how flexible are you
willing to be
but there are things that are
incompatible and then the question is
like kind of so what
or what is the bigger framework that
those are
or the context in which those are aren't
compatible
um excitingly though this will be
tomorrow
um
I'll put the paper in the chat this is
uh so Jay Benjamin Fallen days will join
for a guest stream
a potential mechanism for gibsonian
resonance
behavioral entrainment emerges from
local homeostasis in an unsupervised
Reservoir Network
so I hope to
um
see A Accessible presentation on
modern gibsonian
modeling
and drawing out some similarities and
differences that are real or perceived
with active inference
ever and then anyone else
this
gibsonian or computational approach
there's also
links to
um to the question is uh perception
inferential or is it is it more direct
perception
and I
don't really find a good argument that
discusses the evidence for for
inferential approach to perception or
ecological direct perception
so I was wondering which way to go
yes there's so many
um angles on this one of them is maps
not territories so whatever it is that
perception really is for ants or humans
or computers we're going to model it
with Bayesian inference so that's a very
strong position because then it leaves
the other person debating about how Maps
really are while we're over here using
modern computational tools to do
statistical modeling and inference so
that kind of sidesteps the discussion
about the ontology of what is actual
perception and puts it into the
instrumentalist camp
and then in terms of evidence the first
thing that comes to mind is
we're perceiving colors and shapes in
our blind spot
so no of course it's not direct
perception you don't have photoreceptors
there
is that
conclusive
so okay this is this is mainly if it's
fission visual perception is mainly uh
used as a as a way to discuss perception
but it gets more difficult if you talk
about about for example pay or olfactory
perception and then and then the
question is is all perception
inferential or are there is does it
depend on
the kind of perception you're talking
about is it visual or auditory
um
and I'm wondering
yeah it's it's um
there's definitely a lot of nuance once
we step outside of the clear invisible
visual setting or the tangible and
comprehensible tactile setting
those are very immediate
but analogy is certainly apply to other
sensory modalities and again whatever
the modality is
one can say we're using Bayesian
inference
so let's just say whatever direct
perception means
how is it being statistically modeled is
this
yeah so the direct perception the way I
understand the difference is that uh our
priors are determine uh uh
have a big influence and what we have uh
as a perception and in the direct
perception our priors don't influence
what we perceive
uh but maybe I need to
black and white here
lay it out and see if it's been argued
that way elsewhere or
what exactly would reduce your
uncertainty about that question and if
no one has laid it out so simply then it
will be making a contribution
Jonathan
yeah I I didn't have this this answers
the question at all but I think
your question there about the prize
um we it may be that we have
um very accurate incoming information
and therefore independent of what our
priority you open the door and you don't
know what's behind the door
um the the prize will still have some
effects but they may have much less
effect than in than the incoming
information
um so I I don't think it's a matter of
one uh sort of one form of perception
using priors and others not I think it's
just a balance between how strong those
priors are
that's my my take on it
awesome yeah exactly
um in the Bayesian inference modeling
setting
we could model
a case where
accurate information is coming in
which is to say that the generative
model has high precision
on the information coming in it's
updating priors a lot it has high
attention or salience so it's like
whatever the new information is it just
updates it's prior to that so to the
posterior becomes the incoming
observation that's the special case of
like a Time series filter with a depth
of one it's like whatever the last data
point is just go to that so that is
functionally direct perception
whereas if we have ambiguous information
coming in there's low Precision on
sensory data priors are not updating a
lot in low salience it's low attention
then the belief moving forward
is reflecting the a pre the a priori
stance the prior stance so
Bayesian inference is just giving us
computational tools and formal methods
to describe that possibility
so we can go from something that's being
updated
time Point by time point or not
but I've never seen any kind of useful
model presented other than just the
appeal to direct perception not saying
it's not there Brock and then anyone
else
um I just wanted to bring
um of something that
ali
um continues to remind people because I
think it's hard it's easy to forget or
not or look over here is that uh
we're using all this language about uh
you know vision and um in the context of
it like us a human and the brain and all
of this and
um actually
it's not uh that that sort of entails a
belief about the about active inference
being
um
physical
like that the blanket is physical that
the senses and the observations all
these you know actions are always kind
of purely physical
um or that the epistemic value the
pragmatic value well that's epistemic
that's information that's you know
pragmatic that's always action it's not
um so cleanly
that is actually an informational State
space that we're talking about that the
blankets in
right so it doesn't
um
if you remember that I guess is what I'm
saying
um
and that it is constrained in a physical
substrate like
you are in a space you are in a Time
um there are
you know additional there is a
generative process outside of you that
is constraining your generative model
like
there is a constraint of affordances
like you can't have
um
you you can't be a thing with an
attracting
characteristics like State space
um and like ignore that completely sort
of
um you will always have priors so to ask
like yeah what what
how is it that we have like direct
perception or
when are when are we ignoring our priors
that's back to this anthropomorphic like
purely physical thing it's like when do
the you know beliefs that statistical
beliefs kind of um
cancel out or something right with the
when when are they purely reflective of
the sense you know of the blank
um
that doesn't mean that you're ignoring
your priors it just means that like like
Daniel was saying is just a you know a
well-fit you know high resolution High
um
the expectation and the the blanket
state does the evolver are
uh you know low surprise
so
thanks thanks again just physically
constraint that's that's the important
part is you can't
you have to have beliefs you have to
have prayers and so
thank you yes it is a double-edged sword
with the appeals to physical organisms
because on one hand it kind of anchors
how we think about these informational
spaces and relationships
on the other hand it naturally leads to
a lot of important and interesting
questions
that very often it's mapped not
territory but if one doesn't know the
territory and is just learning the map
then it's it's no
bad thing
to ask questions that bump up against
map territory but to be aware that there
is a map territory relationship
that becomes clearer and clearer
as people learn about cartography how
the maps are built and why and as people
explore territory
and then
um yes some of the key
uh citations in this area
one of them would be the emperor's new
Markov blankets
which was from we we had some live
streams with yellow in 2021
and then most recently the blanket trick
which is a whole other story we're not
going to go into it again but I'll put
the link there
and um
it captured a lot of this discourse on
the blankets
okay in our last
um other than just the last thing um so
Jonathan I think wrote imagine seeing
something in low light or bright light
there's a Continuum of how strong the
priors will will
um influence I believe the inference
and that has been captured like in
psychophysics which is from a long time
ago
small changes in brightness are more
detectable in a dim room
so the question is how to bring these
kinds of empirical cognitive phenomena
into our statistics and inference
modeling methods
and
in the eyes of some
it's it's a done deal
so here Maxwell is saying like this was
never an issue
you get information theory in dynamical
systems theory naturally
so it was never an issue that doesn't
mean every single researcher was aware
of it but it wasn't an issue
and then
um
the map territory fallacy fallacy which
I'll also put in the chat
where they I we I think we've even
brought this up previously but
they argue that fep
is the ideal model
of these kinds of map territory
situations
but a lot of the frustrations are
related to different understandings and
framings of map territory so
anyone please feel free to raise your
hand just bring up any comments or
daughter question
otherwise we'll take a look at one or
two more of the chapter one questions
that people had
ever yes
yeah so so as you probably remember I I
work as a physical therapist and I treat
people with mainly chronic pain and I it
is quite uh essential to make a stand as
to
uh uh perception being inferential or
direct because if uh pain is the
experience that comes about uh
by integrating priors and likelihoods
and you could make a case that the
priors are
let's say male adaptive and are
determining the the ongoing pain
experience
and instead of the likelihood uh in this
in this example
but
um yeah
if that's not the case then that has
quite some implications for the way I
treat people so that's why it's also
very clinically relevant to uh yeah
to have a good good uh reason to say
okay I'm going for this inferential
computational explanation of uh
perception so just to to highlight where
this uh question is coming from
thank you yeah that's a great point and
So like
um we're going to come to this later but
with cognitive modeling so let's just
say again whether or not it's really
direct or inferential in the world we're
going to be using Bayesian inference as
a tool
and we find that somebody is engaging in
some behavior that we don't prefer it's
like a child doing something that we
don't prefer or the person has expressed
that they don't prefer it or however it
is
with cognitive models
it's possible to ask or differentiate
kind of like a differential diagnosis
and Ryan Smith and others have done a
lot of work in this area like is the
person repeatedly taking this action
because they think that it leads to
positive outcomes
so that it's a learning failure to
understand the consequences of action
or do they have a preference for that
outcome those are two different clinical
situations
does this person prefer
X outcome and they are taking the
approach that makes sense at which point
you'd want to be like hey it's really
cool to be X
and then
figured that they'll take the right path
or do they know that they want to be
somewhere but they are not clicking on
the consequences of their action in
taking them to that goal so that kind of
differential diagnosis and like you said
is it like that the person has
um a high prior likelihood on well
people like me have this kind of pain at
which point maybe any stimuli might
interpret it as as that type of pain
because it's likely right why not
or
is it
a sensory attenuation is it a
sensitivity to something it it could be
any number of things so we can still use
this differential diagnosis
paradigm
a little bit one step closer to being
operationalized it doesn't need to pull
back to like direct or inference
philosophy
within the maps that we can make you can
still ask about the relative
contribution of prior's likelihood
sensory observations and so on
but I think that's these are the exact
kinds of application Avenues
where hearing people's like insights and
questions on which parts of this
framework are relevant for them as they
continue to go deeper into it it's like
that's what is great to see
okay
well
let's look at where we're going to be
going in the coming weeks and chapters
so we're having our second discussion on
chapter one chapter one there was no
equations it was giving some big
overviews and laying out a lot of the
big picture for active inference as the
authors see it
then we're gonna have two weeks as we go
into a lot of the substance of the book
chapter two three four and five okay
what are those chapters gonna be about
well chapter two and three
are going to describe the low road and
the high road to active inference and
we're going to talk probably a ton about
low road and high road
um
the low road and and we can come up with
just tables and tables of concordances
it'll be really fun the low road is in a
way asking how
how with Bayesian statistics this is how
we're going to do it this is how these
Maps work this is how these models work
active inference is about cognitive
modeling how are those models being
implemented Bayes theorem not every
Bayesian statistics equation has to do
with cognition and action and perception
you could have a Bayesian statistics
model of something that wasn't an active
agent but we're interested in the
generative models
that do perception
and action and planning as an inference
challenge
and then in the case of brains that has
been called the Bayesian brain approach
so how Bayes theorem chapter 2 low road
foreign
is coming from the imperative for
persistence or for survival or for
repeated measurement so
treat it lightly when we talk about the
imperative for persistence and I know
we've had some discussions even last
week on what about these kinds of
um seemingly self-inflicted injuries and
all of this but just from a statistical
perspective
something has to persist long enough to
be measured as being that thing
otherwise you won't measure it at that
thing like if you're taking measurements
every hour and the cloud is dissipating
every five seconds
you're not going to see that cloud
if the cloud is dissipating on the
hourly time scale and you're measuring
it every five seconds there's going to
be some equations that you can use to
model the cloud moving or growing and
changing so that's coming from The High
Road this imperative
for persistence
which becomes operationalized
in a way that's compatible with Bayesian
statistics through this concept of
self-evidencing and the reduction of
surprise about one's own perceptions
like if you're unsurprised that you're
in homeostasis
you're going to be persisting as that
kind of thing if you find yourself
surprised at your homeostatic parameters
it won't be long until you are not that
kind of thing
chapters two and three low road how
High Road why
those are importantly the low road to
active inference High Road two active
inference
that's going to bring us to chapter four
generative models of active inference
that's where we're going to see the
kernel
that is situated on one hand using Bayes
theorem as a how
and explaining self-organization and
persistence in terms of why
chapter 5 is then going to talk about
the setting where octave inference
generative models have been studied most
extensively to this point which is the
mammalian nervous system
so that is going to bring up a lot of
examples from the Central and the
peripheral nervous system of mammals and
talk about how generative models have
been used
to study those kinds of phenomena that
people are interested in from motor
Behavior to decision making
that's the first half of the book so
we've kind of like
gone in the skateboarding ramp or like
the ski jump or whatever it is that is
like chapter one it's kind of like going
over the edge
and now
we're going to have more equations
and some technical pieces are going to
be introduced along these two roads
and just like with everything it's many
coats of paint
so
read through it and and ask questions
every question is important so even if
it's a very big what does this letter
mean why is this here
what would this mean if it doesn't
didn't have to be this way
how does this apply to this setting
how does this help us do this or that
like any structure of question
if each of us can come up with a few
we'll have many
and um
yeah
specifically let's just look at what
will come to in chapter two and then
we'll close
William James my thinking first and last
and always for the sake of my doing this
kind of speaks to this essential
embedding of action in inference in
active inference
we start with perception as inference so
that's going to cover some of the topics
that we talked about today
Box 2 1 is going to introduce Bayes
theorem and probabilistic reasoning
there's going to be an example that
comes back a few times with a person
holding something in their hand it could
be a frog or an apple and then it's
going to jump or not
and we're going to model our uncertainty
about what that object is based upon
what we observe it to do
there's going to be some discussion of
basic statistical Concepts
like support and expectation
that is going to be applied in the
setting of The generative process and
the generative model
process like the niche model like the
cognitive agents
action as inference previously we were
talking about perception as inference
now action is going to be treated as a
variable that you can do
inference on
both perception and action can be used
to reduce discrepancies which will also
have a technical definition
variational free energy is going to be
introduced as a statistical measure that
helps us bounce surprise
and it will be shown what that means
and then expected free energy is going
to be introduced as a way that is as a
way that different policies about the
future different sequences of actions
can be compared with each other
special cases of expected free energy
collapse to various other important
settings like if there's no information
to glean you can pursue pragmatic value
if there's no pragmatic value to pursue
you can purely pursue informational ends
and that's the end of the low road
thank you everybody
farewell